The first idea I'd like to suggest is that we all
الفكرة الأولى التي أود طرحها هي أننا كلنا
love music a great deal. It means a lot to us.
كلنا نحب الموسيقى. إنها تعني الكثير لنا
But music is even more powerful if you don't just listen to it, but you make it yourself.
لكن الموسيقى تكون أكثر تأثيراً إذا قمت بعزفها بنفسك بدلاً من الاستماع إليها
So, that's my first idea. And we all know about the Mozart effect --
إذاً هذه هي فكرتي الأولى . ونحن جميعاً قد سمعنا بتأثير موزارت
the idea that's been around for the last five to 10 years --
هذه الفكرة التي بدأت في الانتشار خلال الخمس أو العشر سنوات الأخيرة
that just by listening to music or by playing music to your baby [in utero],
إنه عند الاستماع إلى الموسيقى أو عند العزف لطفلك
that it'll raise our IQ points 10, 20, 30 percent.
فإن معدل ذكائه سيزيد بنسبة 10 ، 20 ، 30 بالمئة
Great idea, but it doesn't work at all.
فكرة عظيمة لكنها ليست صحيحة إطلاقاً
So, you can't just listen to music, you have to make it somehow.
لذا لا يكفي أن تستمع إلى الموسيقي لابد من صنعها بطريقة ما
And I'd add to that, that it's not just making it,
وأنا أود أن أضيف أن الموضوع لا يتعلق فقط بعزف الموسيقى
but everybody, each of us, everybody in the world
لكن كل شخص ، أي واحد منا ، أي شخص في العالم
has the power to create and be part of music in a very dynamic way,
لديه القدرة على إبداع وأن يكون جزءا من الموسيقى بصورة أكتر حيوية وديناميكية
and that's one of the main parts of my work.
وهذا هو الجزء الأساسي من عملي
So, with the MIT Media Lab, for quite a while now,
لذلك، قمنا ولفترة طويلة مع مختبر معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا لوسائل الإعلام
we've been engaged in a field called active music.
كنا مهتمين بمجال يدعى الموسيقى النشطة
What are all the possible ways that we can think of
ما هي كل الطرق الممكنة التي يمكننا أن نفكر فيها
to get everybody in the middle of a musical experience,
لكي نمكن كل شخص من خوض تجربة موسيقية
not just listening, but making music?
ليس فقط الاستماع ، بل صنع الموسيقى
And we started by making instruments for some of the world's greatest performers --
وبدأنا بعمل معدات لبعض المؤديين العظماء --
we call these hyperinstruments -- for Yo-Yo Ma, Peter Gabriel, Prince,
نطلق عليها "المعدات الخارقة" -- ليو يو ما ، بيتر جابريل ، برينس
orchestras, rock bands. Instruments where they're all kinds of sensors
فرق الأوركسترا ، فرق الروك، معدات فيها جميع الحساسات
built right into the instrument, so the instrument knows how it's being played.
وضعت بصورة صحيحة في المعدات، بحيث تعرف كل أداة منها كيف تُعزَف
And just by changing the interpretation and the feeling,
ويمكن فقط بتغيير وتفسير الأحاسيس
I can turn my cello into a voice, or into a whole orchestra,
أن أقوم بتحويل الكمان إلى صوت أو إلى أوركسترا كاملة
or into something that nobody has ever heard before.
أو إلى شيء لم يسمعه شخص من قبل
When we started making these, I started thinking, why can't we make
عندما بدأنا عمل ذلك ، بدأت أفكر لماذا لا يمكننا صنع
wonderful instruments like that for everybody,
أدوات رائعة لأي شخص
people who aren't fantastic Yo-Yo Mas or Princes?
أشخاص ليسوا يو يو ماس أو برينسس؟
So, we've made a whole series of instruments.
لذا قمنا بعمل سلسلة كاملة من الأدوات
One of the largest collections is called the Brain Opera.
واحدة من أكبر المجموعات تدعى أوبرا الدماغ
It's a whole orchestra of about 100 instruments,
هي أوركسترا كاملة تتكون من 100 أداة
all designed for anybody to play using natural skill.
كلها مصممة لأي شخص باستخدام مهارات طبيعية
So, you can play a video game, drive through a piece of music,
لذا ، يمكنك أن تقوم بلعب لعبة فيديو والقيام بعزف قطعة موسيقى
use your body gesture to control huge masses of sound,
استخدم لفتات جسدك وإيماءته للتحكم في كميات ضخمة من الصوت
touch a special surface to make melodies, use your voice to make a whole aura.
المس سطوح خاصة لعمل مقطوعات موسيقية ، استخدم صوتك لعمل جوقة كاملة
And when we make the Brain Opera, we invite the public to come in,
وعندما قمنا بعمل أوبرا الدماغ دعونا الناس للحضور
to try these instruments and then collaborate with us
لتجربة هذه الأدوات والتعاون معنا
to help make each performance of the Brain Opera.
للمساعدة في تطوير عمل أوبرا الدماغ
We toured that for a long time. It is now permanently in Vienna,
قمنا بعمل جولات لفترة طويلة ، والآن أوبرا الدماغ موجودة بصورة دائمة في فيينا
where we built a museum around it.
حيث قمنا بإنشاء متحف خاص بها
And that led to something which you probably do know.
وهذا قاد لشيء ربما تعرفونه
Guitar Hero came out of our lab,
قيتار هيرو خرج من مختبرنا
and my two teenage daughters and most of the students at the MIT Media Lab
وابنتاي المراهقتان وأغلب طلاب المختبر
are proof that if you make the right kind of interface,
هم اثبات حي أننا قمنا بعمل النوع الصحيح من الواجهات
people are really interested in being in the middle of a piece of music,
الناس حقا مهتمين بأن يكونوا جزء من مفطوعة موسيقية
and playing it over and over and over again.
وإعادة عزفها مرة تلو مرة.
So, the model works, but it's only the tip of the iceberg,
إذا النموذج يعمل لكن هذا فقط قمة جبل الجليد
because my second idea is that it's not enough just to want
لأن فكرتي الثانية أنه ليس كافيا أنك ترغب
to make music in something like Guitar Hero.
بعزف الموسيقى على أداة مثل غيتار هيرو
And music is very fun, but it's also transformative.
والموسيقى شيء مرح ، لكنها أيضا تحويلية
It's very, very important.
إنها مهمة جدا جدا
Music can change your life, more than almost anything.
الموسيقى يمكن أن تغير حياتك أكثر من أي شيء آخر
It can change the way you communicate with others,
يمكنها أن تغير طريقة تواصلك مع الآخرين
it can change your body, it can change your mind. So, we're trying
يمكنها أن تغير جسدك ، عقلك ، لذا نحن نحاول
to go to the next step of how you build on top of something like Guitar Hero.
أن نصل للمرحلة الثانية لكيفية مواصلة البناء على شيء مثل غيتار هيرو
We are very involved in education. We have a long-term project
نحن مشاركون جدا بالتعليم . ولدينا مشروع طويل المدى
called Toy Symphony, where we make all kinds of instruments that are also addictive,
اسمه لعبة السميفونية حيث قمنا بصنع جميع المعدات الجذابة
but for little kids, so the kids will fall in love with making music,
لكن للأطفال ، لذا سيقع الأطفال في حب عزف الموسيقى وتأليفها
want to spend their time doing it, and then will demand to know how it works,
سيرغبون في قضاء وقتهم في فعل ذلك، ومن ثم سيطلبون معرفة كيف تعمل هذه الأشياء،
how to make more, how to create. So, we make squeezy instruments,
كيف يمكن عمل المزيد ، كيف نبتكرها، لذا عملنا معدات مضغوطة ،
like these Music Shapers that measure the electricity in your fingers,
مثل هذه الأشكال للموسيقية التي تقيس الكهرباء في أصابعك
Beatbugs that let you tap in rhythms -- they gather your rhythm,
اضرب الحشرات التي ستفيدك في الإيقاع -- انها تقوم بتجميع ايقاعك
and like hot potato, you send your rhythm to your friends,
وقم بحب البطاطا الساخنة وعندها سترسل الايقاع إلى أصدقائك
who then have to imitate or respond to what your doing --
الذين سيقومون بتقليدك أو الاستجابة لما فعلته
and a software package called Hyperscore, which lets anybody use lines and color
و حزمة برمجيات تدعى هايبر سكور والتي ستمكن أي شخص من استخدام الخطوط والألوان
to make quite sophisticated music. Extremely easy to use, but once you use it,
لعمل موسيقى متمرسة ومتطورة ، من السهل استخدامها ، لكن بمجرد استخدامه مرة واحدة
you can go quite deep -- music in any style. And then, by pressing a button,
يمكن الذهاب لأعمق من ذلك، موسيقى من أي نوع ، ومن ثم بضغطة زر،
it turns into music notation so that live musicians can play your pieces.
تتحول إلى نوتة موسيقية وبذا يمكن للموسيقيين أن يقوموا بعزف مقطوعاتك
We've had good enough, really, very powerful effects with kids
لدينا تأتير جيد ، قوي ، حقيقي على الأطفال
around the world, and now people of all ages, using Hyperscore.
أناس كثر حول العالم يستخدمون هايبر سكور الآن
So, we've gotten more and more interested in using these kinds of creative activities
ولذا صرنا مهتمين أكثر باستخدام هذا النوع من الابتكارات
in a much broader context, for all kinds of people
في سياق أوسع ، ولكل أنواع البشر
who don't usually have the opportunity to make music.
الذين لا يملكون الفرصة لعمل الموسيقى
So, one of the growing fields that we're working on
لذا ، واحد من المجالات الواعدة التي نعمل عليها
at the Media Lab right now is music, mind and health.
في المختبر هي الموسيقى , العقل والصحة
A lot of you have probably seen Oliver Sacks' wonderful new book called
كثير منك قد يكون سمع بكتاب أوليفر ساكس الجديد
"Musicophilia". It's on sale in the bookstore. It's a great book.
"ميوزيكفيليا" هو متوفر في المكتبات . إته كتاب عظيم
If you haven't seen it, it's worth reading. He's a pianist himself,
إنه كتاب يستحق أن تقرأه إذا لم تقرأه من قبل
and he details his whole career of looking at and observing
وذكر تفاصيل حياته المهنية من النظر والبحث عن
incredibly powerful effects that music has had on peoples' lives in unusual situations.
تأثير القوة الغير اعتيادية للموسيقى على حياة البشر في ظروف غير اعتيادية
So we know, for instance, that music is almost always the last thing
لذا نحن نعرف، لوهلة أن الموسيقي هي آخر شيء
that people with advanced Alzheimer's can still respond to.
يمكن للأشخاص الذين يعانون من مراحل الزهايمر المتأخرة أن يستجيبوا إليه
Maybe many of you have noticed this with loved ones,
ربما بعضكم انتبهوا لهذا الشيء مع أشخاص يحبونهم
you can find somebody who can't recognize their face in the mirror,
ربما تجد شخص لا يستطيع أن يتعرف على وجهه في المرآة
or can't tell anyone in their family, but you can still find a shard of music
ولا يستطيعون التحدث مع أشخاص من أسرته، لكن يمكنك أن تجد قطعة موسيقي
that that person will jump out of the chair and start singing. And with that
بحيث هذا الشخص سيقفز من الكرسي وسيبدأ الغناء وبهذا
you can bring back parts of people's memories and personalities.
يمكنك إعادة أجزاء من ذاكرة الناس وشخصياتهم
Music is the best way to restore speech to people who have lost it through strokes,
الموسيقى هي أفضل طريقة لإعادة النطق للأشخاص الذين فقدوا القدرة على النطق نتيجة للصدمات
movement to people with Parkinson's disease.
والحركة للأشخاص الذين يعانون من مرض باركنسون
It's very powerful for depression, schizophrenia, many, many things.
إنها علاج ذو تأثير قوي للإحباط وانفصام الشخصية وأشياء أخرى كثيرة
So, we're working on understanding those underlying principles
لذا نحن نعمل على فهم هذه المبادئ الأساسية
and then building activities which will let music really improve people's health.
ونقوم بعمل أنشطة تمكن الموسيقى من تحسين صحة الناس
And we do this in many ways. We work with many different hospitals.
ونحن نفعل ذلك بعدة طرق. نحن نعمل مع عدة مستشفيات
One of them is right near Boston, called Tewksbury Hospital.
واحد منهم بالقرب من بوسطن. اسمه مستشفى تيوكسبري
It's a long-term state hospital, where several years ago
إنه مستشفى حكومي ، قبل عدة سنوات
we started working with Hyperscore and patients with physical and mental disabilities.
بدأنا العمل بهايبر سكور مع المرضى ذوي الإعاقات الحسية والعقلية
This has become a central part of the treatment at Tewksbury hospital,
أصبح هذا جزء رئيسي من العلاج في المستشفى
so everybody there clamors to work on musical activities.
لذا الجميع يصنعون ضوضاء من أجل العمل في نشاطات موسيقية
It's the activity that seems to accelerate people's treatment the most
انها نشاطات يبدو أنها تسرع عملية العلاج بأسرع صورة ممكنة
and it also brings the entire hospital together as a kind of musical community.
وهي تجمع كل الناس في المستشفى مع بعض كنوع من المجتمع الموسيقي
I wanted to show you a quick video of some of this work before I go on.
أود عرض فيديو قصير يظهر جزء من العمل قبل أن أواصل
Video: They're manipulating each other's rhythms.
فيديو: انهم يتلاعبون بايقاعات بعضهم البعض
It's a real experience, not only to learn how to play and listen to rhythms,
انها تجربة حقيقية ، ليس فقط لتعلم كيفية العزف والاستماع للايقاعات
but to train your musical memory and playing music in a group.
لكن لتدريب ذاكرتك الموسيقية والعزف في مجموعة
To get their hands on music, to shape it themselves, change it,
ليضعوا أيديهم على الموسيقى وتشكيلها بأنفسهم وتغييرها
to experiment with it, to make their own music.
ليعيشوا التجربة معها، ليصنعوا موسيقاهم الخاصة
So Hyperscore lets you start from scratch very quickly.
لذا هايبر سكور يمكنك من البداية من الصفر بسرعة
Everybody can experience music in a profound way,
أي شخص يمكنه تجريب الموسيقى بطريقة معمقة
we just have to make different tools.
نحن فقط بحاجة لصنع أدوات مختلفة
The third idea I want to share with you is that music, paradoxically,
الفكرة الثالثة التي أود مشاركتكم إياها هي الموسيقى المتناقضة
I think even more than words, is one of the very best ways we have
لا أستطيع التعبير عن أفكاري بالكلمات ، إنها من أفضل طرقنا
of showing who we really are. I love giving talks, although
لعرض من نحن حقيقة ، أنا أحب التحدث ، ولكن رغم ذلك
strangely I feel more nervous giving talks than playing music.
أنا أشعر بعصبية بشكل غريب عند الحديث أكثر من عزف الموسيقى
If I were here playing cello, or playing on a synth, or sharing my music with you,
إذا كنت هنا أعزف الكمان أو أتشارك موسيقاي معكم
I'd be able to show things about myself that I can't tell you in words,
لكنت قادراً على عرض إظهار أشياء عن نفسي لا أستطيع التعبير عنها بالكلمات
more personal things, perhaps deeper things.
أشياء شخصية أكثر ، ربماا أشياء أكثر عمقاً
I think that's true for many of us, and I want to give you two examples
أنا أظن ان هذا حقيقي بالنسبة لنا، و أود عرض بعض الأمثلة
of how music is one of the most powerful interfaces we have,
لكيف أن الموسيقي هى أكثر الواجهات قوة التي نمتلكها
from ourselves to the outside world.
لأنفسنا مع العالم الخارجي
The first is a really crazy project that we're building right now, called
الأول هو مشروع مجنون حقا نقوم ببانئه حاليا اسمه
Death and the Powers. And it's a big opera,
دايث أند باور "الموت والقوى" وهي أوبرا كبيرة
one of the larger opera projects going on in the world right now.
وهي واحد من أعظم أعمال الأوبرا في العالم الآن
And it's about a man, rich, successful, powerful, who wants to live forever.
وتدور قصتها عن رجل غني ، ناجح ، قوي، يود أن يعيش للأبد
So, he figures out a way to download himself into his environment,
لذا تخيل طريقة لتحميل نفسه في بيئته
actually into a series of books.
في سلسلة من الكتب في الحقيقة
So this guy wants to live forever, he downloads himself into his environment.
هذا الشخص أراد أن يعيش للأبد، وحمل نفسه في بيئته
The main singer disappears at the beginning of the opera
المغني الرئيسي يختفي في بداية الأوبرا
and the entire stage becomes the main character. It becomes his legacy.
و كل المنصة تصبح الشخصية الأساسية، إنها تصبح إرثه
And the opera is about what we can share, what we can pass on to others,
والأوبرا عن ما يمكننا أن نتشاركه، ماذا يمكننا أن نمرره للآخرين
to the people we love, and what we can't.
الناس الذين نحبهم، وما لا نستطيع
Every object in the opera comes alive and is a gigantic music instrument,
كل كائن في الأوبرا يأتي حيا على شكل أداة موسيقية عملاقة
like this chandelier. It takes up the whole stage. It looks like a chandelier,
كهذه الثريا. التي تحجز حيزا كبيرا من المنصة إنها تبدو كثريا
but it's actually a robotic music instrument.
لكنها في الحقيقة أداة موسيقية آلية
So, as you can see in this prototype, gigantic piano strings,
كما تشاهدون في النموذج ، أوتار البيانو العملاقة
each string is controlled with a little robotic element --
كل وتر يتحكم فيه عنصر آلي صغير
either little bows that stroke the strings, propellers that tickle the strings,
إما انحناء بسيط يلمس الأوتار، مراوح تداعب الأوتار
acoustic signals that vibrate the strings. We also have an army of robots on stage.
إشارات صوتية تهز الأوتار. لدينا أيضا جيش من الروبوتات على المنصة
These robots are the kind of the intermediary between the main character, Simon Powers,
هولاء الآليون هم من النوع الوسيط بين الشخصية الرئيسية ، سيمون باورز
and his family. There are a whole series of them, kind of like a Greek chorus.
وعائلته. هناك سلسلة كاملة منه ، إنهم كالجوقة الإغريقية
They observe the action. We've designed these square robots that we're testing right now
إنهم يرصدون الحركة. لقد صممنا هولاء الرجال الآليون مربعي الشكل والذين نختبرهم حاليا
at MIT called OperaBots. These OperaBots follow my music.
في ام اي تي اسمهم اوبرا بوتس. انهم يتبعون موسيقاي
They follow the characters. They're smart enough, we hope,
و بتتبعون الشخصيات. انهم أذكياء بما فيه الكفاية. نحن نأمل
not to bump into each other. They go off on their own.
ألا يصطدموا ببعضهم البعض، وألا تنفجر من تلقاء نفسها
And then they can also, when you snap, line up exactly the way you'd like to.
وعندئذ يمكنهم من تلقاء نفسهم، عندما تفاجئهم ، أن يصطفوا بالطريقة التي تريد
Even though they're cubes, they actually have a lot of personality.
رغم أنهم مكعبو الشكل، لديهم الكثير من الهوية
The largest set piece in the opera is called The System. It's a series of books.
أكبر قطعة هي سستم " النظام" وهي سلسلة من الكتب
Every single book is robotic, so they all move, they all make sound,
كل كتاب منها عبارة عن روبوت. لذا عندما يتحركون جميعا ، ينتجون أصواتا جميعا
and when you put them all together, they turn into these walls,
وعندما نضعهم جميعا مع بعضهم ، يتحولون إلى حوائط
which have the gesture and the personality of Simon Powers. So he's disappeared,
والتي لها شخصية سيمون باورز ، لذا اختفى
but the whole physical environment becomes this person.
لكن كل البيئة الموجودة تصبح هذا الشخص
This is how he's chosen to represent himself.
هذه الطريقة التي اختارها ليقدم نفسه
The books also have high-packed LEDs on the spines. So it's all display.
الكتب أيضا تحوي شاشات مسطحة ، هذا كله عرض
And here's the great baritone James Maddalena as he enters The System.
وها هو باريتون جيمس العظيم يدخل في النظام
This is a sneak preview.
هذا هو العرض الأولي
This premieres in Monaco -- it's in September 2009. If by any chance you can't make it,
هذا العرض في موناكو، سبتمبر 2009، في حالة جاءتكم فرصة للذهاب
another idea with this project -- here's this guy building his legacy
فكرة أخرى مع هذا المشروع، هذا هو الشاب الذي يقوم ببناء إرثه
through this very unusual form, through music and through the environment.
بصورة غير طبيعية من خلال الموسيقى والبيئة
But we're also making this available both online and in public spaces,
لكن نحن نعمل على جعل ذلك متاحاً من خلال الانترنت والمساحات العامة
as a way of each of us to use music and images from our lives
كطريقة لكل واحد منا لاستخدام الموسيقى وصور من حياتنا
to make our own legacy or to make a legacy of someone we love.
لعمل إرثنا الخاص أو إرث شخص نحبه
So instead of being grand opera, this opera will turn into what we're
لذا بدلا من الأوبرا العملاقة" قراند أوبرا" هذه الأوبرا ستتحول إلى
thinking of as personal opera.
إلى ما نفكر فيه كأوبرا شخصية
And, if you're going to make a personal opera, what about a personal instrument?
وإذا كنت ستقوم بعمل أوبرا شخصية ، فماذا عن أدوات وأجهزة شخصية
Everything I've shown you so far -- whether it's a hyper-cello for Yo-Yo Ma
كل ما قمت بعرضه لكم -- سواء كان الكمان الخارق ليو يو ما
or squeezy toy for a child -- the instruments stayed the same and are valuable
أو أداة النفخ لطفل -- هذه الأدوات تبقى كما هي وتظل قيمة
for a certain class of person: a virtuoso, a child.
لفئة معينة من الشخص أو الموهوب أو الطفل
But what if I could make an instrument that could be adapted
لكن ماذا إذا قمنا بعمل أداة قابلة للتحور
to the way I personally behave, to the way my hands work,
على حسب طريقة تصرفي الشخصي, على حسب طريقة عمل يدي
to what I do very skillfully, perhaps, to what I don't do so skillfully?
على حسب ما أقوم به بمهارة شديدة، وعلى حسب ما لا أقوم به بمهارة؟
I think that this is the future of interface, it's the future of music, the future of instruments.
أنا أعتقد أن هذا هو مستقبل الواجهة, هذا هو مستقبل الموسيقى ومستقبل الأدوات
And I'd like now to invite two very special people on the stage,
وأود دعوة شخصين مميزين للمنصة
so that I can give you an example of what personal instruments might be like.
حتى أتمكن من إعطاء مثال لكيف ستبدو الأجهزة الشخصية
So, can you give a hand to Adam Boulanger, Ph.D. student from
لذا ، يمكنكم التصفيق لآدم بولنجير طالب الدكتوراه من
the MIT Media Lab, and Dan Ellsey. Dan,
معهد ماسوتشستس ودان السي. دان
thanks to TED and to Bombardier Flexjet, Dan is here with us today
شكرا لتيد وبومبارديل فلكسجيت ، دان معنا هنا اليوم
all the way from Tewksbury. He's a resident at Tewksbury Hospital.
قادم من تيوكسبري ، هو مفيم في المستشفى
This is by far the farthest he's strayed from Tewksbury Hospital, I can tell you that,
هذه أبعد مسافة قطعها من المستشفى ، أنا أؤكد ذلك
because he's motivated to meet with you today and show you his own music.
لأنه كان متحمسا لرؤيتكم ومقابلتكم اليوم ويريكم موسيقاه
So, first of all, Dan, do you want to say hi to everyone and tell everyone who you are?
لذا، بادئ ذي بدء، هل تود أن تقول مرحبا للجميع وتعرفهم بنفسك؟
Dan Ellsey: Hello. My name is Dan Ellsey. I am 34 years old and I have cerebral palsy.
دان السي: مرحبا. اسمي دان السي. عمري 34 سنة .أعاني من شلل دماغي
I have always loved music and I am excited to be able to conduct
كنت دائما محبا للموسيقى وأنا أشعر بالحماس لتوصيل
my own music with this new software.
موسيقاي الخاصة بالبرنامج الجديد
Tod Machover: And we're really excited to have you here, really Dan. (Applause)
تود ماكوفر: ونحن متحمسين لوجودك هنا، دان.(تصفيق)
So we met Dan about three years ago, three and a half years ago,
نحن التقينا مات قبل 3 سنوات ونصف
when we started working at Tewksbury. Everybody we met there was fantastic,
عندما بدأنا العمل في المستشفى، كل من قابلناه هناك كان رائعا
did fantastic music. Dan had never made music before, and it turned out
يعزف موسيقى رائعة. دان لم يعزف قبل ذلك واتضح أنه
he was really fantastic at it. He's a born composer.
كان رائعا بحق في ذلك. انه مؤلف بالفطرة
He's very shy, too.
و خجول جدا أيضاً
So, turned out he's a fantastic composer, and over the last few years has been
لذا . اتضح انه مؤلف بارع وخلال السنوات الأخيرة كان
a constant collaborator of ours. He has made many, many pieces.
متعاون ثابت معنا. قام بتأليف الكثير من المقطوعات الموسيقية
He makes his own CDs. Actually, he is quite well known in the Boston area --
قام بعمل أسطواناته الخاصة. في الحقيقة إنه معروف في منطقة بوسطن
mentors people at the hospital and children, locally, in how to make their own music.
يرشد الناس في المستشفى والأطفال لكيفية عمل موسيقاهم الخاصة
And I'll let Adam tell you. So, Adam is a Ph.D. student at MIT, an expert in music
وسأجعل آدم يتحدث إليكم. آدم طالب دكتوراة في ام اي تي، خبير موسيقي
technology and medicine. And Adam and Dan have become close collaborators.
تقني وطبي. وآدم ودان أصبحا متعاونين متقاربين
What Adam's been working on for this last period is not only how to have Dan
ما كان يقوم بعمله آدم خلال الفترة السابقة ليس فقط جعل دان
be able easily to make his own pieces,
يقوم بعمل قطعه الموسيقية بسهولة
but how he can perform his piece using this kind of personal instrument.
لكن كيف يقوم بعزف فطعه باستخدام هذا النوع من الأجهزة الشخصية
So, you want to say a little bit about how you guys work?
لذا ، أنتم تودون مشاهدة القليل عن كيفية عمل هؤلاء الشباب؟
Adam Boulanger: Yes. So, Tod and I entered into a discussion
آدم بولنجير: نعم ، آدم وأنا دخلنا في مناقشة
following the Tewksbury work and it was really about how Dan is an expressive
عن عمل تيوكسبري وكان حقيقة عن دان وكيف أنه شخص معبر
person, and he's an intelligent and creative person. And it's in his face,
وهو ذكي ومبدع. هذا يبدو من وجهه
it's in his breathing, it's in his eyes. How come he can't perform
في تنفسه، في عينيه. كيف لا يمكنه ان يعزف
one of his pieces of music? That's our responsibility, and it doesn't make sense.
قطعه الموسيقية؟ هذه مسئوليتنا ولا معنى لها
So we started developing a technology that will allow him with nuance,
لذا بدأنا تطوير تقنية تمكنه مع فارق بسيط
with precision, with control, and despite his physical disability, to be able to do that,
بدقة ، بالتحكم على الرغم من إعاقته الجسدية، أن يكون قادراً
to be able to perform his piece of music.
على عزف قطعه الموسيقية
So, the process and the technology --
لذا ، المعالجات والتقنية
basically, first we needed an engineering solution. So, you know,
أساسا، أولا نحن احتجنا لهندسة الحل، لذا، أنتم تعرفون
we have a FireWire camera, it looked at an infrared pointer.
نحن نملك كاميرا حرارية، تنظر إلى مؤشر للأشعة تحت الحمراء
We went with the type of gesture metaphor that Dan was already used to
نحن اتبعنا طريقة لتشبيهه والتعبير عنه كالتي كان يستخدمها
with his speaking controller.
مع أداة التحكم في الكلام
And this was actually the least interesting part of the work, you know,
وكان هذا في الحقيقة أقل الأجزاء إثارة في العمل , أنتم تعلمون
the design process. We needed an input; we needed continuous tracking;
عملية التصميم. نحن كنا بحاجة لمدخلات، تتبع متواصل
in the software, we look at the types of shapes he's making.
في البرمجيات سننظر إلى الأشكال التي يقوم بصنعها
But, then was the really interesting aspect of the work, following the engineering part,
لكن، كان الجانب الأكثر إثارة من العمل بعد الجزء الهندسي
where, basically, we're coding over Dan's shoulder at the hospital
عندما كنا نقوم بالترميز على كتف دان في المستشفى
extensively to figure out, you know, how does Dan move?
على نطاق واسع محاولين تخيل ، كما تعلمون، كيف يتحرك دان؟
What's useful to him as an expressive motion?
ماهي أفضل حركة تعبر عنه؟
You know, what's his metaphor for performance?
أنتم تعلمون ماهو التشبيه له للحصول على أداء
What types of things does he find
ماهو نوع الأشياء التي كان يجدها
important to control and convey in a piece of music?
مهمة للتحكم والنقل في القطعة الموسيقية
So all the parameter fitting, and really the technology
كل العناصر كانت ملائمة، وحقيقة التقنية
was stretched at that point to fit just Dan.
التي قمنا بتمديدها لتلائم دان فقط
And, you know, I think this is a perspective shift. It's not that our technologies --
و ، أنتم تعلمون، أنا أظن أن هذا تحول في المفاهيم، ليس تقنياتنا
they provide access, they allow us to create pieces of creative work.
هي التي توفر الدخول ، إنها تسمح لنا بالقيام بعمل مبدع
But what about expression? What about that moment when an artist delivers
لكن ماذا عن التعبير، ماذا عن اللحظة التي يوصل فيها الفنان
that piece of work? You know, do our technologies allow us to express?
قطعته الموسيقية؟ أنتم تعلمون، هل تسمح لنا التقنيات بالتعبير؟
Do they provide structure for us to do that? And, you know, that's a personal relationship
هل توفر لنا التعليمات للقيام بذلك؟و ، أنتم تعلمون ، أن علاقة الشخص
to expression that is lacking in the technological sphere. So, you know,
في التعبير تفتقر إلى الطبقة التقنية، لذا أنتم تعلمون
with Dan, we needed a new design process, a new engineering process
مع دان نحن احتجنا إلى عملية تصميم جديدة ، عملية هندسية جديدة
to sort of discover his movement and his path to expression that allow him to perform.
لتقوم بفرز حركاته وطريقة تعبيره لتسمح له بالعزف
And so that's what we'll do today.
وهذا هو ما لدينا اليوم
TM: So let's do it. So Dan do you want to tell everyone
تي ام: دعنا نقوم بذلك، دان هل تود إخبار الجميع
about what you're going to play now?
عن ماذا ستقوم بعزفه الآن؟
DE: This is "My Eagle Song."
دي اي:إنها "ماي ايقل سونق" أغنية صقري
TM: So Dan is going to play a piece of his, called "My Eagle Song".
تي ام: إذا سيقوم دان بعزف مقطوعة يسميها" ماي إيقل سونق"
In fact, this is the score for Dan's piece,
في الحقيقة هذة نقاط عن هذه المقطوعة
completely composed by Dan in Hyperscore.
إنها مؤلفة بالكامل بواسطة دان باستخدام هايبر سكور
So he can use his infrared tracker to go directly into Hyperscore.
لذا يمكنه استخدام متتبعه للأشعة تحت الحمراء ليذهب مباشرة لهايبر سكور
He's incredibly fast at it, too, faster than I am, in fact.
إنه سريع بصورة مدهشة إنه في الحقيقة أسرع مني أنا
(Laughter)
ضحك
TM: He's really modest, too.
تي ام: وهو مزاجي أيضا
So he can go in Hyperscore. You start out by making melodies and rhythms.
لذا يمكنه الذهاب إلى هايبر سكور. أنت تبدأ بعمل أنغام وإيقاع
He can place those exactly where he wants.
هو يستطيع وضع هذه الأشياء في أي مكان يريده بالضبط
Each one gets a color. He goes back into the composition window,
كل واحدة منها تأخذ لونا، تذهب إلى شاشة التأليف
draws the lines, places everything the way he wants to. Looking at the Hyperscore,
ترسم الخطوط، تضع كل شيء في مكانه، بالنظر إلى هايبر سكور
you can see it also, you can see where the sections are,
انتم تستطيعون رؤية مكان المقاطع
something might continue for a while, change, get really crazy and then end
هذا الشيء ربما يستمر لفترة ، يتغير، يصير مجنونا وفي النهاية
up with a big bang at the end.
تحصل على شيء عظيم في النهاية
So that's the way he made his piece, and as Adam says,
هذه هي الطريقة التي نقوم فيها بعمل المقطوعة وآدم يقول
we then figured out the best way to have him perform his piece.
نحن نبحث بعد ذلك عن أفضل طريقة ليقوم بعزف مقطوعته
It's going to be looked at by this camera, analyze his movements,
الكاميرا ستنظر إليه تقوم بتحليل حركاته
it's going to let Dan bring out all the different aspects of his music that he wants to.
ستمكنه من إظهار كل ما يود إظهاره في الموسيقى
And you're also going to notice a visual on the screen.
وأنتم سوف تلاحظون عرض بصري على الشاشة
We asked one of our students to look at what the camera is measuring.
طلبنا من إحد الطلاب أن ينظر إلى ما تقوم الكاميرا بقياسه
But instead of making it very literal, showing you exactly
لكن بدلا من أن نقوم بعمل ذلك حرفيا بعرض ما تتبعه الكاميرا
the camera tracing, we turned it into a graphic that shows you the basic
حرفيا, نحن نقوم بتحويل ذلك إلى صور تتعقب الحركات
movement, and shows the way it's being analyzed.
الأساسية وكيفية تحليلها
I think it gives an understanding of how we're picking out movement from what
أنا أظن أن هذا يعطي فهم لكيفية استخراج الحركة
Dan's doing, but I think it will also show you, if you look at that movement,
مما يقوم دان بعمله، لكن أعتقد أن هذا سيريكم إذا كنتم تنظرون لحركة دان
that when Dan makes music, his motions are very purposeful, very precise,
هذا عندما يقوم دان بعزف الموسيقى، حركاته هادفة ودقيقة جدا
very disciplined and they're also very beautiful.
منضبطة جدا وأيضا جميلة جدا
So, in hearing this piece, as I mentioned before, the most important thing is
إذا عند الاستماع إلى هذه القطعة الموسيقية. كما ذكرت سابقاً أهم شيء هو أن
the music's great, and it'll show you who Dan is.
الموسيقى عظيمة وستريكم من هو دان
So, are we ready Adam?
إذاُ هل نحن جاهزون يا آدم؟
AB: Yeah.
أجل
TM: OK, now Dan will play his piece "My Eagle Song" for you.
تود: حسنا ، الآن سيقوم دان بعزف مقطوعته "أغنية لصقري" من أجلكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
TM: Bravo.
تي ام:برافو